I think all of us have been interested, at one time or another,
أعتقد اننا جميعا شغل بالنا في وقت او اخر,
in the romantic mysteries of all those societies that collapsed,
تلك الألغاز المتعلقة بانهيار المجتمعات المندثرة,
such as the classic Maya in the Yucatan, the Easter Islanders,
مثل مجتمعات مايا القديمة و شبه جزيرة يوكاتان, وجزيرة الفصح
the Anasazi, Fertile Crescent society, Angor Wat, Great Zimbabwe
و الأناسازي: من سكان أمريكا الأصليين - و الهلال الخصيب و أنكر وات:بـ كمبدوديا, و زمبابوي القديمة
and so on. And within the last decade or two,
و هلم جرا. و خلال العقد او العقدين الماضيين,
archaeologists have shown us that there were environmental problems
وضح لنا علماء الاثار انه كانت هناك مشكلات بيئية
underlying many of these past collapses.
تسببت في العديد من تلك الإنهيارات المجتمعية في الماضي.
But there were also plenty of places in the world
و لكن هناك ايضا العديد من المناطق في العالم
where societies have been developing for thousands of years
مجتمعات تمكنت من النمو لالاف السنين
without any sign of a major collapse,
بدون أية بادرة للإنهيار,
such as Japan, Java, Tonga and Tikopea. So evidently, societies
كـ اليابان و جاوا بـإندونيسيا و تونجا و تيكوبية في جنوب المحيط الهادئ. ليبدوا واضحا جدا, أن هناك مجتمعات
in some areas are more fragile than in other areas.
في بعض البقاع من العالم تكون ضعيفة عنها في مناطق اخرى.
How can we understand what makes some societies more fragile
كيف يمكننا ان نفهم ما الذي يجعل بعض المجتمعات أكثر هشاشة
than other societies? The problem is obviously relevant
من مجتمعات أخرى؟ من الواضح ان المشكلة وثيقة الصلة
to our situation today, because today as well, there are
بوضعنا الراهن اليوم, لأن اليوم هناك ايضا
some societies that have already collapsed, such as Somalia
بعض المجتمعات قد إنهارت بالفعل, الصومال على سبيل المثال
and Rwanda and the former Yugoslavia. There are also
و راواندا ويوغوسلافيا السابقة. هناك ايضا
societies today that may be close to collapse, such as Nepal, Indonesia and Columbia.
اليوم مجتمعات على وشك الإنهيار, كـ نيبال و إندونيسيا وكولومبيا.
What about ourselves?
ماذا عن أنفسنا؟
What is there that we can learn from the past that would help us avoid
ما الذي يحمله لنا الماضي لنتعلمه ليساعدنا في تفادي
declining or collapsing in the way that so many past societies have?
الإنتكاس او الإنهيار بالطريقة التي إنهارت بها المجتمعات في الماضي؟
Obviously the answer to this question is not going
من البديهي أن تكون الإجابة على هذا التساؤل لن يكون
to be a single factor. If anyone tells you that there is a single-factor
عاملا واحدا. لو أخبرك احدهم أن يتعلق بعاملا واحدا
explanation for societal collapses, you know right away
يشرح الإنهيارات المجتمعية, لابد أن تعرف على الفور
that they're an idiot. This is a complex subject.
أن هذا الشخص أحمق. لأن هذا موضوع معقد.
But how can we make sense out of the complexities of this subject?
لكن كيف يمكننا -من بين تلك التعقيدات- إستخلاص شئ منطقي؟
In analyzing societal collapses, I've arrived at a
بتحليلي للإنهيارات المجتمعية, توصلت إلى
five-point framework -- a checklist of things that I go through
هيكل من خمسة نقاط: قائمة فحص من خمسة اشياء استخدمها
to try and understand collapses. And I'll illustrate that five-point
وأحاول فهم الإنهيارات. و سأبين تلك النقاط الخمس
framework by the extinction of the Greenland Norse society.
إبان إنهيار المجتمع النرويجي على جزيرة جرين لاند.
This is a European society with literate records,
هذا مجتمع أوروبي بسجلات موضوعية,
so we know a good deal about the people and their motivation.
لذلك نحن نتعرف الكثير عن ذلك المجتمع ودوافعه.
In AD 984 Vikings went out to Greenland, settled Greenland,
في عام 984 ذهب الإسكندنافيون إلى جزير جرين لاند, وإستقروا هناك
and around 1450 they died out -- the society collapsed,
و في العام 1450 ماتوا .. إنهار المجتمع,
and every one of them ended up dead.
كان مصير كل واحد فيهم هو الموت.
Why did they all end up dead? Well, in my five-point framework,
لماذا كان مصيرهم هكذا؟ حسنا, في هيكلي ذو الخمس نقاط,
the first item on the framework is to look for human impacts
العنصر الاول فيه هو أن نلقي نظرة على التأثير البشري
on the environment: people inadvertently destroying the resource
على البيئة: حيث يدمر البشر -غير مبالين- المصادر
base on which they depend. And in the case of the Viking Norse,
التي يعتمدون عليها في العيش. وفي حالة الإسكندنافين النرويج,
the Vikings inadvertently caused soil erosion and deforestation,
تسبب الإسكندنافيون في تآكل التربة و إقتلاع الاشجار,
which was a particular problem for them because
و التي كانت مشكلة كبيرة بالنسبة لهم لأن
they required forests to make charcoal, to make iron.
لأنهم كانت تعوزهم الغابات من أجل الفحم .. وسيلتهم لتصنيع الحديد.
So they ended up an Iron Age European society, virtually
فكان مصيرهم الفعلي بإنتهاء العصر الحديدي لمجتمع أوروبي
unable to make their own iron. A second item on my checklist is
بعدم قدرتهم على تصنيع الحديد. العنصر الثاني فى قائمتي هو
climate change. Climate can get warmer or colder or dryer or wetter.
التغير المناخي. المناخ من الممكن أن يكون أكثر دفئا أو أكثر برودة .. اكثر جفافا أو رطوبة.
In the case of the Vikings -- in Greenland, the climate got colder
بالنسبة للإسكندنافيين في جزير جرين لاند, تغير المناخ ليكون أكثر برودة
in the late 1300s, and especially in the 1400s. But a cold climate
و ذلك في نهاية القرن الرابع عشر, خاصة مع بدايات القرن الخامس عشر. ولكن المناخ البارد
isn't necessarily fatal, because the Inuit -- the Eskimos inhabiting
لا يكون بالضرورة مهلكاو لأن الإنويتيين - شعب الإسكيمو الذي سكن
Greenland at the same time -- did better, rather than worse,
جرين لاند في نفس الحقبة - تعايش بشكل أفضل بدلا أن يتهاوى
with cold climates. So why didn't the Greenland Norse as well?
بسبب الأحوال الجوية الباردة. فلماذا لم لم يفعل ذلك سكان جرين لاند النرويج ايضا؟
The third thing on my checklist is relations with neighboring
العنصر الثالث على قائمتي هو علاقات الجوار
friendly societies that may prop up a society. And if that
المجتمعات الودودة يدعمها سلوكها في البقاء. أما إذا
friendly support is pulled away, that may make a society
تلاشي هذا العامل, فمن الممكن ان يؤدي بالمجتمع
more likely to collapse. In the case of the Greenland Norse,
ان ينهار على أكثر الإحتمالات ترجيحا. في حالة جرين لاند النرويجية
they had trade with the mother country -- Norway --
كان المجتمع يقوم على مال التجارة مع موطنهم الأم, النرويج
and that trade dwindled: partly because Norway got weaker,
و لكن تلك التجارة كسدت جزئيا لأن النرويج أصبحت أكثر ضعفا,
partly because of sea ice between Greenland and Norway.
و إلى حد ما بسبب البحر المتجمد بين النرويج و جزيرة جرين لاند.
The fourth item on my checklist is relations with hostile societies.
العامل الرابع على قائمتي هو العلاقات مع المجتمعات المعادية.
In the case of Norse Greenland, the hostiles were the Inuit --
و في حالة نرويج جرين لاند, المعادين كانوا الإنويتيين: الإسكيمو,
the Eskimos sharing Greenland -- with whom the Norse
شعب الإسكيمو تشارك التعايش مع النرويج على جزيرة جرين لاند والذين
got off to bad relationships. And we know that the Inuit
أقاموا معهم علاقات سيئة. و نحن نعرف أن الإسكيمو
killed the Norse and, probably of greater importance,
قتلوا النرويجيين وذلك من المحتمل بسبب في غاية الاهمية,
may have blocked access to the outer fjords, on which
ربما بسبب غلقهم الطريق إلى المضائق و التي كان
the Norse depended for seals at a critical time of the year.
يستخدمها النرويجيون لصيد كلاب البحر في الوقت الحرج من العام.
And then finally, the fifth item on my checklist is the political,
و أخيرا, العنصر الخامس على قائمتي و هو العوامل السياسية, و
economic, social and cultural factors in the society that make it
الإقتصادية و الثقافية التي يتألف منها المجتمع
more or less likely that the society will perceive and solve its
و التي قد تساعد المجتمع بدرجة كبيرة أو صغيرة على إدراك وحل
environmental problems. In the case of the Greenland Norse,
المشكلات البيئية. و في حالة نرويج جزيرة جرين لاند
cultural factors that made it difficult for them
كان العامل الثقافي عائقا امامهم
to solve their problems were: their commitments to a
لإيجاد حلول لمشكلاتهم و التي تمثلت بإلتزاماتهم تجاه
Christian society investing heavily in cathedrals; their being
المجتمع المسيحي بتكريسهم الكثير من الوقت والجهد فى بناء الكاتدرائيات, وكونهم
a competitive-ranked chiefly society; and their scorn for the Inuit,
- على الأغلب - مجتمعا أعلى تنافسية و مع إزدرائهم للإسكيمو,
from whom they refused to learn. So that's how the five-part
و الذين رفضوا أن يتعلموا منهم. وهكذا يعتبر هيكل العمل ذى الخمس نقاط
framework is relevant to the collapse and eventual extinction of the Greenland Norse.
وثيقة الصلة بإنهيار و إندثار المجتمع النرويجى على جزيرة جرين لاند بلا رجعة.
What about a society today?
ما رايكم لو تكلمنا عن مجتمعا معاصرا؟
For the past five years, I've been taking my wife and kids to
طوال السنوات الخمس الماضية,كنت أصحب زوجتي وأولادي إلى
Southwestern Montana, where I worked as a teenager
جنوب غرب ولاية مونتانا, حيث كنت أعمل هناك وانا مراهق
on the hay harvest. And Montana, at first sight, seems
في جمع القش. و مونتانا تبدو للذى يراها لأول وهلة
like the most pristine environment in the United States.
مثل اية مكان محتفظ بفطرته فى الولايات المتحدة
But scratch the surface, and Montana suffers from serious problems.
و لكن هذه نظرة سطحية, لأن مونتانا لديها مشكلات جسيمة.
Going through the same checklist: human environmental impacts?
و بتطبيق نفس قائمة الفحص: التأثير البشري على البيئة.
Yes, acute in Montana. Toxic problems from mine waste
يوجد, و بشكل خطير فى مونتانا. المشكلات المتعلقة بمخلفات المناجم
have caused damage of billions of dollars.
التي تسببت فى أضرار تقدر بمليارات الدولارات.
Problems from weeds, weed control, cost Montana nearly
مشكلات الحشائش الضارة والتحكم فيها تكلف مونتانا -تقريبا-
200 million dollars a year. Montana has lost agricultural areas
200 مليون دولار سنويا. حصيلة الأراضى الزراعية التي فقدت
from salinization, problems of forest management,
بسبب تزايد نسبة الملوحة, و مشكلات إدارة الغابات,
problems of forest fires. Second item on my checklist:
و مشكلات حرائق الغابات. النقطة الثانية على قائمتي:
climate change. Yes -- the climate in Montana is getting warmer
التغير المناخي. نعم ..المناخ يصبح أكثر دفئا فى ولاية مونتانا
and drier, but Montana agriculture depends especially on irrigation
و أكثر جفافا, لكن الزراعة فى مونتانا تعتمد على الري
from the snow pack, and as the snow is melting -- for example,
من كتل الجليد, و مع ذوبان هذا الجليد, على سبيل المثال,
as the glaciers in Glacier National Park are disappearing --
الأنهار الجليدية في الحديقة النهر الجليدى القومية نراها تختفى,
that's bad news for Montana irrigation agriculture.
و هذه أخبار سيئة بالحديث عن الري الزراعي لـ مونتانا.
Third thing on my checklist: relations with friendlies
النقطة الثالثة على قائمتي: هى علاقات الجوار
that can sustain the society. In Montana today, more than half of
و العنصر الذي فى إمكانه الحفاظ على المجتمع. اليوم فى مونتانا, أكثر من نصف
the income of Montana is not earned within Montana,
الدخل لا يكتسب داخلها,
but is derived from out of state: transfer payments from
و لكنه يصب إليها من خارجها على هيئة معاشات من
social security, investments and so on --
التأمين الإجتماعي, و إستثمارات خارجها إلى أخره,
which makes Montana vulnerable to the rest of the United States.
و هو ما يجعل مونتانا منتقدة من بقية الولايات الأمريكية.
Fourth: relations with hostiles. Montanans have the same problems
رابعا: طبيعة العلاقات مع المعاديين. سكان مونتانا لديهم نفس المشكلات
as do all Americans, in being sensitive to problems
التي لدى الامريكان بأنهم شديدي التأثر بالمشكلات التي
created by hostiles overseas affecting our oil supplies,
يختلقها معتدين قادمين من وراء البحار, مؤثرين بذلك على إمدادتنا من البترول,
and terrorist attacks. And finally, last item on my checklist:
و الهجمات الإرهابية. و أخيرا, العنصر الأخير على قائمتي:
question of how political, economic, social, cultural attitudes
و هو سؤال حول كيف أن العوامل الإقتصادية و الإجتماعية, و التوجهات الثقافية
play into this. Montanans have long-held values, which today
تلعب دورها في هذا الامر. سكان مونتانا متعلقين بمجموعة من القيم منذ أمد بعيد واليوم
seem to be getting in the way of their solving their own problems.
يبدوا ان تلك القيم تقف في طريقهم لحل مشكلاتهم.
Long-held devotion to logging and to mines and to agriculture,
واهبين أنفسهم على طول الخط بقطع ونقل الأشجار و العمل بالمناجم و الزراعة,
and to no government regulation; values that worked well
بلا أي تشريعات تنظم كل هذا. القيم التى نجحوا بها
in the past, but they don't seem to be working well today.
في الماضي , لا يبدوا أنها تعمل لصالحهم اليوم.
So, I'm looking at these issues of collapses
إذن, أنا ابحث في تلك الموضوعات الخاصة بالإنهيارات
for a lot of past societies and for many present societies.
لتلك المجتمعات التي إنهارت فى الماضي و العديد من مجتمعات اليوم.
Are there any general conclusions that arise?
هل هناك أية إستنتاجات عامة تبرز لنا؟
In a way, just like Tolstoy's statement about every unhappy marriage
إلى مدى مثل عبارة تولستوي عن كل زيجة تعيسة
being different, every collapsed or endangered society is different --
هي أنها مختلفة, و كل مجتمع إنقرض أو إنهار هو مجتمع مختلف..
they all have different details. But nevertheless, there are certain
كل منها لديه تفاصيله المختلفة عن الاخر. و مع ذلك هناك خيوط معينة
common threads that emerge from these comparisons
و مشتركة تبرز لنا بعقد المقارانات
of past societies that did or did not collapse
بين المجتمعات الماضية التي إنهارت أم تلك التى لم تنهار
and threatened societies today. One interesting common thread
و المجتمعات المهددة اليوم. الخيط المشترك بينها
has to do with, in many cases, the rapidity of collapse
له علاقة في معظم الحالات بتسارع الإنهيار
after a society reaches its peak. There are many societies
بعد أن يصل المجتمع لذروة التقدم, هناك العديد من المجتمعات
that don't wind down gradually, but they build up -- get richer
التي لا يتباطئ نموها تدريجيا, و لكنها تبنى, وتصبح أكثر ثراءا
and more powerful -- and then within a short time, within a few decades
و اكثر قوة, ثم خلال فترة وجيزة , خلال عقود قليلة
after their peak, they collapse. For example,
بعد قمة تقدمهم , ينهارون, على سبيل المثال,
the classic lowland Maya of the Yucatan began to collapse in the
مجتمع المايا القديم في الأراضى المنخفضة لشبه جزيرة يوكاتان بدأ فى الإنهيار فى
early 800s -- literally a few decades after the Maya were building
بداية القرن التاسع, حَرفيا بعد عقود من بنائها لـ
their biggest monuments, and Maya population was greatest.
اثارها المعمارية , و وصول عدد السكان للدرجة القصوى.
Or again, the collapse of the Soviet Union took place
و من جديد, سقوط الإتحاد السوفيتي تم
within a couple of decades, maybe within a decade, of the time
خلال عقدين من الزمان او ربما عقد واحد
when the Soviet Union was at its greatest power.
و هذا عندما كان الإتحاد السوفيتي فى أوج قوته.
An analogue would be the growth of bacteria in a petri dish.
تشبيهي لهذا هو نمو البكتيريا فى (طبق بتري) = يستخدم فى المعامل
These rapid collapses are especially likely where there's
هذه الإنهيارات السريعة تكون مرجحة بشكل خاص عندما يكون هناك
a mismatch between available resources and resource consumption,
عدم توافق بين المصادر المتاحة و إستهلاكها
or a mismatch between economic outlays and economic potential.
أو عدم توافق بين النفقات الإقتصادية و القدرات الإقتصادية.
In a petri dish, bacteria grow. Say they double every generation,
في (طبق بتري) تنمو البكتيريا. دعنا نقول أنهم يتضاعفون كل جيل,
and five generations before the end the petri dish is 15/16ths empty,
و مع خمسة أجيال يصبح 15/16 من طبق بتري مستنزفا,
and then the next generation's 3/4ths empty, and the next generation
و مع الجيل الجديد يصبح ¾ الطبق مستنزف و مع الجيل الذى يليه
half empty. Within one generation after the petri dish still
يتبقى نصف الطبق. خلال جيل واحد مع بقاء طبق بتري
being half empty, it is full. There's no more food and the bacteria have collapsed.
نصف ممتلئ,يصبح ممتلئ‘‘ عن أخره. فلا يصبح هناك طعام و تنهار البكتريا.
So, this is a frequent theme:
إذن, هذه تيمة متكررة
societies collapse very soon after reaching their peak in power.
أن المجتمعات تنهار بشكل سريع بعد بلوغها أوج قوتها.
What it means to put it mathematically is that, if you're concerned
ما الذي يعنيه هذا بتمثيله رياضيا, هل لو انك مهتما بـ
about a society today, you should be looking not at the value
مجتمعا معاصرا فلا ينبغي ان تنظر لقيمة
of the mathematical function -- the wealth itself -- but you should
الدالة الرياضية,الثروة نفسها, بل ينبغي عليك
be looking at the first derivative and the second derivatives
النظر إلى المشتق الاول و الثاني
of the function. That's one general theme. A second general theme
لتلك الدالة. و هذه تيمة عامة. وهناك تيمة عامة اخرى
is that there are many, often subtle environmental factors that make
انه هناك العديد من العوامل البيئية الطفيفة التي تجعل
some societies more fragile than others. Many of those factors
بعض المجتمعات أكثر هشاشة عن غيرها, و العديد من تلك العوامل
are not well understood. For example, why is it that in the Pacific,
ليست مفهومة بشكل كافي,ما الذي فى المحيط الهادى
of those hundreds of Pacific islands, why did Easter Island end up as
من بين الاف الجزر فيه, ينتهي مآل جزر الهادئ
the most devastating case of complete deforestation?
لأضخم عملية تدمير كامل للغابات؟
It turns out that there were about nine different environmental
و إتضح أنه كان هناك أكثر من 9 عوامل بيئية
factors -- some, rather subtle ones -- that were working against
بعضها عوامل ضئيلة, كانت تعمل ضد
the Easter Islanders, and they involve fallout of volcanic tephra,
سكان جزيرة الفصح, تضمنت سقوط المخلفات البركانية,
latitude, rainfall. Perhaps the most subtle of them
موقع الجزيرة , سقوط الامطار, و ربما اكثر العوامل ضآلة
is that it turns out that a major input of nutrients
أن النسبة الأكبر للعناصر الغذائية
which protects island environments in the Pacific is from
التي تحمي بيئة الجزر فى المحيط الهادي تأتي
the fallout of continental dust from central Asia.
من التراب القاري من اسيا الوسطى.
Easter, of all Pacific islands, has the least input of dust
جزيرة الفصح, من بين جزر المحيط الهادي صاحبة الحظ الأقل من هذا التراب
from Asia restoring the fertility of its soils. But that's
القادم من اسيا ليجدد خصوبة التربة. ولكن
a factor that we didn't even appreciate until 1999.
هذا العنصر لم نعطيه قدره حتى العام 1999.
So, some societies, for subtle environmental reasons,
إذن هناك مجتمعات, و بسبب عوامل بيئية ضئيلة,
are more fragile than others. And then finally,
تصبح أكثر هشاشة عن غيرها. و أخيرا,
another generalization. I'm now teaching a course
هناك تعميم اخر, و لأني اقوم بتدريس برنامج
at UCLA, to UCLA undergraduates, on these collapses
لطلبة جامعة كاليفورنيا, و هو عن الإنهيارات
of societies. What really bugs my UCLA undergraduate students is,
لتلك المجتمعات, و الذي أزعج طلبتي هناك
how on earth did these societies not see what they were doing?
هو كيف لم ترى تلك المجتمعات نتيجة ما تفعله؟
How could the Easter Islanders have deforested their environment?
كيف لسكان جزيرة الفصح أن يدمروا الغابات
What did they say when they were cutting down the last palm tree?
ما الذي كانوا يفكرون فيه وهم يقتلعون اخر شجرة نخيل؟
Didn't they see what they were doing? How could societies
ألم يروا نتيجة فعلهم؟ كيف لمجتمعات
not perceive their impacts on the environments and stop in time?
الا يدركوا تأثيرهم على البيئة و يتوقفون في الوقت المناسب؟
And I would expect that, if our human civilization carries on,
و أتوقع لو إستمرت الحضارة البشرية على هذا النحو
then maybe in the next century people will be asking,
فمن المحتمل أن يتساءل الناس في القرن القادم
why on earth did these people today in the year 2003 not see
لماذا لم يرى الناس في عام 2003
the obvious things that they were doing and take corrective action?
الاشياء الواضحة التي يقومون بها ويقومون بإجراءات تصحيحية؟
It seems incredible in the past. In the future, it'll seem
يبدو الامر عسير التصديق في الماضي. و في المستقبل سيبدو
incredible what we are doing today. And so I've been
ما نفعله اليوم عسير التصديق ايضا. لذلك كنت
trying to develop a hierarchical set of considerations
احاول ان اضع الامور التي تأخذ فى الإعتبار على شكل هرمي
about why societies fail to solve their problems --
عن الاسباب التي ادت إلى فشل المجتمعات فى حل مشكلاتهم.
why they fail to perceive the problems or, if they perceive them,
و لما اخفقوا في إدراك تلك المشكلات من الاساس, و لو كانوا ادركوها
why they fail to tackle them. Or, if they tackle them,
لماذا لم يتناولوها بالعلاج؟ او لو كانوا شرعوا في ذلك,
why do they fail to succeed in solving them?
لماذا لم ينجحوا في التوصل إلى حلول؟
I'll just mention two generalizations in this area.
سأذكر أمرين حول ذلك يخص كافة المجتمعات المنهارة.
One blueprint for trouble, making collapse likely,
مخطط واحد للمأزق, يجعل الإنهيار محتمل,
is where there is a conflict of interest between the short-term
و هو أنه عندما يكون هناك صراع بين المصلحة على المدى القصير
interest of the decision-making elites and the long-term
و المدى البعيد بين النخبة صانعة القرار
interest of the society as a whole, especially if the elites
بالنسبة للمجتمع ككل, خاصة لو ان تلك النخبة
are able to insulate themselves from the consequences
قادرة على عزل انفسها من عواقب
of their actions. Where what's good in the short run for the elite
أفعالهم. حيث يكون ما هو جيد بالنسبة للنخبة على المدى القصير
is bad for the society as a whole, there's a real risk of the elite
هو سئ بالنسبة للمجتمع ككل و هناك مخاطرة حقيقية من النخبة
doing things that would bring the society down in the long run.
بقيامها بأشياء يسبب في تداعي المجتمع على المدى البعيد
For example, among the Greenland Norse --
على سبيل المثال, في عصر جزيرة جرين لاند النرويجية
a competitive rank society -- what the chiefs really wanted
كان المجتمع شديد التنافس.. الذي اراده المسؤولون حقا
is more followers and more sheep and more resources
هو أتباع اكثر و خراف أكثر ومصادر أكثر
to outcompete the neighboring chiefs. And that led the chiefs
ليتفوقوا في المنافسة على جيرانهم, وهذا قادهم
to do what's called flogging the land: overstocking the land,
لما يسمى بإغراق الأرض: تكدس المخزون ,
forcing tenant farmers into dependency. And that made
مجبرين المزارعين بالأجرة على الإستقلال. و هذا جعل
the chiefs powerful in the short run,
المسؤولين أقوياء على المدى القصير,
but led to the society's collapse in the long run.
و لكنه أدى إلى إنهيار المجتمع على المدى البعيد.
Those same issues of conflicts of interest are acute
تلك الموضوعات المتعلقة بالصراع بين المصالح شديدة الخطورة
in the United States today. Especially because
في الولايات المتحدة اليوم. خاصة
the decision makers in the United States are frequently
لأن صانعي القرار فى الولايات المتحدة وبشكل متكرر
able to insulate themselves from consequences
لديهم القدرة على عزل انفسهم من العواقب
by living in gated compounds, by drinking bottled water
بالعيش في مجمعات سكنية مسورة, و شربهم للمياه المعلبة
and so on. And within the last couple of years,
و هكذا. و خلال السنتين الماضيتين
it's been obvious that the elite in the business world
بدا واضحا ان كبار عالم الأعمال
correctly perceive that they can advance
ادركوا بشكل صحيح أن في إمكانهم أن يتخطوا
their short-term interest by doing things that are
مصلحتهم على المدى القصير وقيامهم بأشياء
good for them but bad for society as a whole,
في صالحهم و ضد المجتمع ككل
such as draining a few billion dollars out of Enron
مثل سحب بلايين الدولارات من شركة إينرون للطاقة - أفلست في عام 2001
and other businesses. They are quite correct
و من أعمال أخرى كذلك. و هم على حق تماما
that these things are good for them in the short term,
أن تلم الإستثمارات جيدة لهم على المدى القصير,
although bad for society in the long term.
بالرغم من أنها ضارة للمجتمع على المدى البعيد.
So, that's one general conclusion about why societies
إذن, هذا إستنتاج عام يبين لماذا تتخذ المجتمعات
make bad decisions: conflicts of interest.
قرارات سيئة: تضارب المصالح.
And the other generalization that I want to mention
و السبب الاخر الذي أود ذكره
is that it's particularly hard for a society to make
أنه يصعب على المجتمع على وجه الخصوص ان يتخذ
quote-unquote good decisions when there is a conflict involving
قرارت جيدة عندما يكون هناك صراع
strongly held values that are good in many circumstances
التمسك القوي بالبقيم (القيم: ليس القيم الأخلاقية) و التي تكون فى صالح المجتمع فى كثير من الاحيان
but are poor in other circumstances. For example,
و لكنها في احيان اخرى تصبح خطر عليه. على سبيل المثال,
the Greenland Norse, in this difficult environment,
في العصر النرويجي لجزيرة جرين لاند, فى تلك البيئة القاسية,
were held together for four-and-a-half centuries
إرتبط المجتمع لأربعة قرون ونصف القرن
by their shared commitment to religion,
بإلتزامهم الديني
and by their strong social cohesion. But those two things --
و التماسك الإجتماعي القوي. و لكن هذين الامرين..
commitment to religion and strong social cohesion --
الإلتزام الديني و التماسك الإجتماعي..
also made it difficult for them to change at the end
جعل عليهم من الصعب التغيير في نهاية المطاف
and to learn from the Inuit. Or today -- Australia.
و ان يتعلموا من الإسكيمو. أو مثال من عالم اليوم, استراليا.
One of the things that enabled Australia to survive
واحدة من الأشياء التي جعلت استراليا تستمر فى الحياة
in this remote outpost of European civilization
تحت ظل الحضارة الأوروبية الموجهة إليهم عن بعد
for 250 years has been their British identity.
لمدة 250 سنة كانت لديهم تلك الهوية البريطانية.
But today, their commitment to a British identity
و لكن الان, إلتزامهم تجاه تلك الهوية
is serving Australians poorly in their need to adapt
يخدم الاستراليين بشكل ضعيف مع حاجتهم للتأقلم
to their situation in Asia. So it's particularly difficult
مع موقفهم من اسيا. لذلك إنه أمر صعب للغاية
to change course when the things that get you in trouble
أن تغير مسارك عندما تصبح الأشياء التي تضعك في مأزق
are the things that are also the source of your strength.
هي نفس الاشياء التى تمثل مصدر قوتك.
What's going to be the outcome today?
ماذا ستكون حصيلة اليوم؟
Well, all of us know the dozen sorts of ticking time bombs
حسنا, كلنا يعلم الانواع العديدة للقنابل الموقوتة
going on in the modern world, time bombs that have fuses
المتاحة في العالم الان. قنابل موقوتة بفتيل
of a few decades to -- all of them, not more than 50 years,
يؤدي إلى إنفجار بعد عقود قليلة..كل تلك القنابل - فى أقل من 50 سنة,
and any one of which can do us in; the time bombs of water,
وأي واحدة منهم سوف تفجر حياتنا. قنبلة المياه الموقوتة,
of soil, of climate change, invasive species,
قنبلة التربة الزراعية, التغيير المناخي, الغزو الإستعماري,
the photosynthetic ceiling, population problems, toxics, etc., etc. --
إنخفاض نسبة البناء الضوئي, مشكلات التلوث, السميات, إلخ إلخ--
listing about 12 of them. And while these time bombs --
قائمة من 12 مشكلة شبيهة. و تلك القنابل الموقوتة
none of them has a fuse beyond 50 years, and most of them
لن تنفجر إحداها قبل 50 عاما, و معظمهم
have fuses of a few decades -- some of them, in some places,
ستنفجر في غضون عقود قليلة-- و بعض تلك القنابل في بعض الاماكن
have much shorter fuses. At the rate at which we're going now,
لديها فتيل اقصر بكثير. في المعدل الجاري اليوم,
the Philippines will lose all its accessible loggable forest
الفليبينيون سوف يفقدون كل الغابات قابلة للإستخدام
within five years. And the Solomon Islands are only
في غضون 5 سنوات. و جزر سلومون -فقط-
one year away from losing their loggable forest,
في غضون عام سوف تفقد كل غاباتها,
which is their major export. And that's going to be spectacular
و التي هي اكبر عنصر يصدرونه. و هذا سيكون له عظيم الأثر
for the economy of the Solomons. People often ask me,
على إقتصاد جزر سلومون. الناس يسألونني,
Jared, what's the most important thing that we need to do
جيريد, ما هو الشئ الاهم الذي نحتاج أن نقوم به
about the world's environmental problems?
تجاه مشكلات العالم البيئية؟
And my answer is, the most important thing we need to do
و إجابتي هي, أن الشئ الأكثر أهمية و الذي نحتاج ان نقوم به هو
is to forget about there being any single thing that is
أن ننسى موضوع ان مسألة أن هناك امرا واحدا
the most important thing we need to do.
مهما علينا القيام به.
Instead, there are a dozen things, any one of which could do us in.
بدلا من ذلك هناك دستة من المشكلات , و أي منها قادر على إبادتنا.
And we've got to get them all right, because if we solve 11,
و لابد من معالجتها جميعا بشكل صحيح, لاننا لو قمنا بحل 11 منها
we fail to solve the 12th -- we're in trouble. For example,
و فشلنا في حل المشكلة الـ 12 فسنكون في ورطة. على سبيل المثال,
if we solve our problems of water and soil and population,
لو قمنا بحل مشكلات المياه والتربة الزراعية و التلوث,
but don't solve our problems of toxics, then we are in trouble.
و لم نقم بحل مشكلة السموم , فسنكون في ورطة.
The fact is that our present course is a non-sustainable course,
الحقيقة هي أن واقعنا الحالي لن يدوم
which means, by definition, that it cannot be maintained.
و الذي يعني بشكل بديهي اننا لن يمكننا الحفاظ عليه.
And the outcome is going to get resolved within a few decades.
و نتيجة ذلك سيتم حلها خلال عقود قليلة.
That means that those of us in this room who are less than
و هذا يعني أن كل الحضور في القاعة
50 or 60 years old will see how these paradoxes are resolved,
دون الـ 50 سنة او الـ 60 سنة سيعيشون تلك المفارقات,
and those of us who are over the age of 60 may not see
و ربما لن يعيش ذلك من فوق الستين
the resolution, but our children and grandchildren certainly will.
و لكن أولادنا وأحفادنا من المؤكد انهم سيفعلوا.
The resolution is going to achieve either of two forms:
النتيجة ستأخذ إحدى شكلين:
either we will resolve these non-sustainable time-fuses
إما أن نتمكن من إبطال مفعول تلك القنابل
in pleasant ways of our own choice by taking remedial action,
بطريقة لطيفة و عن طواعية بإتخاذ إجراءات علاجية,
or else these conflicts are going to get settled
وإلا ستحصل حالة الصراع
in unpleasant ways not of our choice -- namely, by war,
بطريقة غير سارة و سنكون مجبرين عليها.. وأعني, بالحرب,
disease or starvation. But what's for sure is that our
و المرض أو المجاعة. و لكن هذا أمر مؤكد أن
non-sustainable course will get resolved in one way or another
مسارنا الحالي سينتهي بإحدى تلك النتيجتين
in a few decades. In other words, since the theme of this session
وفي عقود قليلة. بمعنى اخر, طالما أن تيمة هذه المحاضرة هي
is choices, we have a choice. Does that mean that we should
توسيع مجال الإختيار, و اننا لدينا إمكانية الإختيار. هل هذا يعني اننا يجب
get pessimistic and overwhelmed? I draw the reverse conclusion.
ان نصبح متشائمين و مثقلين بالأعباء؟ سأوضح الإستنتاج المقابل.
The big problems facing the world today are not at all
المشكلات الكبرى التي تواجه العالم اليوم ليست على الإطلاق
things beyond our control. Our biggest threat is not an asteroid
خارج مجال سيطرتنا. التهديد الأكبر ليس مثل جسم فضائي
about to crash into us, something we can do nothing about.
على وشك الإرتطام بنا, و لا يمكننا القيام تجاهه بردة فعل.
Instead, all the major threats facing us today are problems
على العكس, كل التهديدات الكبرى التي تواجهنا اليوم هي مشكلات
entirely of our own making. And since we made the problems,
هي بالكامل من صنعنا نحن. و طالما تسببنا فيها
we can also solve the problems. That then means that it's
يمكننا أيضا حلها. وهذا يعني إذن
entirely in our power to deal with these problems.
اننا نمتلك القوة للتعامل مع تلك المشكلات.
In particular, what can all of us do? For those of you
ما الذي يمكننا القيام به على وجه التحديد؟ من المهتمين منكم
who are interested in these choices, there are lots of things
بإستخدام قدرته على الإختيار, هناك العديد من الأشياء
you can do. There's a lot that we don't understand,
تستطيع القيام بها. و هناك العديد من الامور التي لا نفهمها,
and that we need to understand. And there's a lot that
و التي نحتاج لفهمها. و هناك العديد من تلك الامور
we already do understand, but aren't doing, and that
نفهمه بالفعل, ولكننا لا نتخذ حيالها أي فعل
we need to be doing. Thank you.
و نحتاج أن نقوم به. أشكركم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)